oh yeah the post-exercise anabolic
window what we're talking about today is
is it actually real now there's a lot of
confusion in this field and I'm gonna
set you straight in just a couple of
minutes in fact I think I can do this in
under 25 but we'll see how derailed I
actually get if you're not familiar with
what I'm talking about the post-exercise
anabolic windows this concept that it's
really important that within 30 or 60 or
90 minutes some number that people seem
to disagree on that you need to get your
nutrients in post-workout if not you'll
minimize your gains or in other words
you won't maximize your gains so this is
based on the concept that your muscle
cells are more sensitive to nutrients
immediately post exercise so if you wait
to consume your food too long you won't
get the maximum amount of gains or
recovery so let's actually answer then
go directly into it I'm not gonna mess
around this time in this episode of 25
minute phys post's exercise anabolic
window so is it real despite what you
may have heard on the internet or on
probably twitter or instagram it's 100%
real make no no questions or mistakes
about it everyone your muscle cells are
absolutely more sensitive to nutrients
posts exercise assuming you did some
reasonably hard exercise now if you just
went for a walk probably doesn't matter
I'm talking about something that was
hard a reasonably hard so yeah again let
me clarify it is 100% real yourselves
are definitely more sensitized to
nutrients particularly carbohydrates and
protein the immediately post exercise or
even during exercise for that matter I
think where the confusion actually
happens this is the next piece though
does it actually matter to you now
that's a big difference so it's not
quite a question whether or not that's a
real physiological phenomena or
questioning does it actually matter for
you and in order for me to answer that I
have to know the context of the question
and this is what actually people get so
confused about is we want to make
blanket statements like yes it's real no
it's not real and we don't want to have
the nuanced discussion about the context
and that's where
truth lies and this is why several
people that you may have heard and they
sound like they're contradicting each
other but they're really talking about
what is quote unquote true in different
situations so let's get into that I'll
show you some examples and I promise you
by the end this video you will not be
Clair confused at all about what's going
on here you'll know exactly what to do
when you should matter about the window
and we you shouldn't care at all so
let's dive into it what I mean by
context is this let's take a couple of
different examples first and foremost
whether or not you should care about the
post exercise anabolic window or the
recovery window whatever you want to
call it depends on your training goal
which or you're trying to maximize well
sniper trophy we try to get stronger or
trying to improve sport performance or
trying to improve marathon running what
are we actually training for that
determines a lot of it how about daily
routine are you training fasted some
people like to wake up in the morning
and consume you know 2 or 300 calories
or less and then workout they feel
better on an empty stomach
that's way different than an athlete
who's training at 7 p.m. after 3 meals
in 3,000 calories so that's gonna
determine how important it is to have
nutrients post exercise or not what
nutrients are we talking about the
answer is different for talking about
protein compared to carbohydrates what
about personal preferences again some
people don't like to eat immediately
post exercise some people prefer that
some people stomachs are more sensitive
they need a half an hour an hour before
they get something in same thing in the
morning let's not force feed our
athletes breakfast if they're not a
breakfast person if it makes them lashes
etc all right now what about logistics
so if you're like an NC double-a athlete
and you're having to leave your strength
conditioning session and go immediately
to an hour and a half a film or two
class or things like that that's
different than somebody who's working
out the evening and then they're sitting
at home so what's going on logistical II
do I have to travel to I have to go to
my next practice so I have media what
else is happening on that end and then
anything else right the context these
are just five or so six examples but
you've got to think through what you're
actually dealing with to understand what
other situations did you factor in the
equation I'm not going to give you them
all I'm gonna ask you to do a little bit
of thinking so
I wanna walk you through one specific
example or two rather so you can have
some tangible things to think about so
what I've done is I'm gonna make you a
little bit of a score sheet okay and
we're talking about the post exercise
new trick window so in other words is it
important in two different training
scenarios for you get your carbohydrates
in really close to or immediately post
exercise and then the same thing for
protein and the two training scenarios
I've come up with our two friends of
mine so on top you'll see Zoila frost oh
there and Zoila is a professional
fighter fights in Muay Thai and
kickboxing and most recently MMA she's a
world champion all right so she's a an
athlete
she's typically gonna train 14 - if it's
up to her more like 18 times a week this
means she's training typically a minimum
of twice per day and often times three
times per day and when I say training I
really mean exercise I don't mean
watching film or walkthroughs that
that's pretty physical and all of those
things so keep that in mind again two to
three training sessions a day six times
a week or more and we'll compare that to
my friend Chris and we'll assume
obviously from the picture they're at
Chris's training goal is hypertrophy now
this is significantly different because
number one the outcome is obviously
different but think about the training
so with someone who try to maximize I
heard you might be lifting every day but
they're very rarely lifting the same
muscle group on multiple days so in this
example if Chris did his legs on Monday
he's probably not going to do things
again on Tuesday at best it'd be
Wednesday probably most realistically
Thursday so really even if he's training
seven days a week most of the time and I
perjured feet scenarios and most you're
gonna train any individual muscle group
three times a week more like twice with
about 72 hours different the soilless
legs get crushed every single workout
right she has to have her quads back two
to three times a day because they're
involved in basically everything she
does right neither one of these is
better than worse but they're different
scenarios so let's start with the top
what about Zoila for carbohydrates is it
important that she gets her carbs in as
close to or immediately a post exercise
as possible well if you look across the
literature in the science that's going
to support this as well as my practical
experience and findings it's incredibly
important
we do not want to waste any time with
getting those carbohydrates in if it's
me I actually prefer they drink them
during the workout but immediately post
or pre is is even better we have two
resynthesize muscle glycogen so the vast
majority of the interview she's got
she's going to get for her workouts come
from the stored glycogen or the
carbohydrates in her muscle the most
direct way to replenish that
carbohydrate is to consume carbohydrate
and again we have less than four hours
typically or maybe five to six to
restore that and we're gonna be doing
that multiple times in a row four or
five six days in a row for eight to ten
to twelve weeks we don't have any time
to mess around we need to get that
carbohydrate and really really fast so
we're in that case we're gonna choose
low fiber a high glycemic index foods to
get that stuff in immediately or as
quickly as you possibly can in terms of
protein for zoila I would actually say
it's the same thing now we'll get into
total protein intake throughout the day
a little bit in a second but this is
logistic concern right so we have we
know that consuming protein post
exercise doesn't harm
muscle glycogen resynthesis so it
doesn't necessarily aid it a whole lot
but it may provide a slight bump to
slightly nothing it's gonna start aiding
in muscle recovery maybe not a whole lot
but some but more importantly here we
just have logistics to consider if we
don't get that stuff in immediately post
exercise when else are we going to eat
she's gonna be training again in a few
hours she's got travel she's got things
to set up she's coaching she's got other
things to do if we wait to eat we're
screwed and so it's really important
that we get that stuff in even for
protein so the carbohydrates is a real
science physiology concern the protein
neurons is is more of a logistics
practical scenario why I would recommend
that for now as we transition to look at
the kristin is most like per trophy or
carbohydrates needed immediately post
exercise for that probably not if you're
gonna be training the muscle group again
the next day you might want to get your
carbohydrates in but again as I already
explained typically frier per trophy you
got at least 48 hours I'm only be more
like 72 hours within that time domain
you're very likely to be able to restore
your car
hydrates as long as you're consuming
enough of those over the next couple of
days now another misconception that we
had ten years ago or so but now it's
sort of gone is the protein here and the
evidence is generally fairly clear here
which and it would support the fact that
your total protein intake throughout the
day and probably honestly even more like
over the course of 36 or 48 hours
matters more than the exact timing so
even for hypertrophy and protein it
doesn't necessarily matter if you have a
pretty mid post or even wait a few hours
just get it in throughout the day now
interestingly we are actually right now
in the middle of a study in which we're
looking at intermittent fasting so the
people that wait to consume their
protein only or all their food rather
within an eight-hour window versus those
that consume it all throughout the day
and the goal here where our study is
different is the goal is actually
maximizing hypertrophy and so we're
gonna see in young well-trained people
whether or not that that timing really
does matter when we give them a really
specific eating scenario okay but for
the most part right now the literature
suggests timing is really fairly
irrelevant and it's really just a matter
of the 24 that almost 48 hour window
that you get enough in that now some
people have misinterpreted this though
to mean that you should wait and that's
not at all what I just said all I said
was it doesn't matter
and so my actually counter to this is
yeah but it doesn't hurt to get it in
immediately and it's not helping
anything to wait there's no added
benefit to waiting it doesn't hurt to
have it immediately in does it help no
it doesn't hurt either so I don't
understand the logic of waiting outside
of having them like a practical scenario
like an athlete or a client doesn't like
eating they have a hard their stomach is
upset they want an hour to settle okay
fine
but I haven't seen any evidence to
suggest it's something you should go out
anyway to do to wait or purpose all that
means is gonna have to have more protein
and higher concentration later on and we
know that's generally not a good thing
protein especially for most like perch
feet it is better consume more
frequently in smaller amounts than big
Bullas at the end of a day or in a
couple
and so while it doesn't particularly
matter when you consume for the most
part a protein fryer per trophy I don't
seen rationale the weight outside of you
know personal preference right so I step
it till still typically say well you
might as well try to get it as soon as
you can
right no harm here so now you've
understood that I'll giving you I'll go
back to this context line I'll give you
a few more of these examples so we've
gone through the hypertrophy thing right
that's hopefully that's very clear what
about someone who's trying to maximize
muscle strength right well hopefully and
I'm not gonna give the answer you got to
think on your own you could go through
protein and carbohydrates and think well
is it important for that person or not
I've also got on this list now things
like repeated sprint ability so this
would be an athlete like Zoila who has
got to do repeated high-intensity stuff
in that particular case it's probably
pretty important to have the
carbohydrates and immediately whether
you want to wait on protein that may or
may not matter an athlete in the middle
of season you have a lot of muscle
damage a lot of banging going on like a
compact or combat sport athlete I
probably wouldn't wait to get their
protein in we want to maximize that
tissue recovery as fast as we can but
again we're not talking hypertrophy here
in terms of daily routine if I have an
individual who fasts I like to work out
again early in the morning either fasted
on which I typically don't advise or
really low calorie and in that situation
since they've now gone 12 14 16 hours
without nutrients I think it's probably
pretty important for those folks to get
both their carbs and protein in pretty
much immediately if you're training at 7
o'clock in the afternoon after 3 or 4
meals it probably doesn't matter at all
for your protein and even maybe your
carbohydrate really doesn't matter all
right you're gonna have now 24 hours to
recover you're gonna be probably just
fine we've gone through the nutrients
and again typically the summer right
here would be carbohydrates the timing
matters a lot more protein reading
regardless to gold probably doesn't
matter a ton personal preference giving
you some examples of that you can think
of more some people like to eat
pre-workout some people don't
us workouts etc logistics I know that
for example in college athletes it's
hard to trust them they've got a lot of
things going on and so a lot of coaches
will say hey you're not leaving the R in
the weight room here until you get that
chocolate milk down and that's not
necessarily because they're super
concerned post-exercise anabolic window
butts more because they're just
concerned they're gonna the athletes
gonna leave then they're gonna need to
make bad nutrition choices or they
become distracted and not drink for two
or three four hours consuming nutrients
etc right and so instead of having a
carbohydrate high carbohydrate high
quality protein meal they might go get
fast food or something else that's a lot
higher in fat which is not great post
exercise alright so some more examples
there and I would encourage you to think
on your own about your own situation to
determine how important or not the post
exercise anabolic window is for your
outcome goal your training goal as well
as the nutrients themselves what I'm
really highlighting here hopefully is
getting to this concept that I like to
say is perspective influences the truth
is I know the truth is is not a word but
it kinda is Thank You Stephen Colbert my
point here being when you're trying to
determine things like is the post
exercise anabolic window quote unquote
real well what what is true or the you
know the right answer it depends them on
on your perspective and hopefully we've
addressed that your understanding this
concept it extends to just about
everything else right so we have very
few black and white answers and a lot
more things that depend on context and
nuance the problem is almost all of us
myself included have a certain set of
lenses in which they're seeing the world
and you can see Karen the picture here
she's zooming in looking very intently
through a certain set of lenses right
what's another saying we all have a
given perspective you might be following
somebody who's a scientist or an expert
in muscle hypertrophy and you can then
pretty much assume they're always
thinking about training adaptations
they're Trisha and programming from the
context of hypertrophy and so what would
be true or a thing
you would always want to do or never
want to do it when the goal is
hypertrophy may or may not be the same
thing for a performance athlete that may
or may not be the same thing for general
health or fat loss again we all have
perspectives we shouldn't be a worried
about that we just need to acknowledge
that so I'm totally cool with you
zooming in it's and then keeping your
eyes down on those two microscopes at
all times but just realizes that there
is a microscope there and that you're
zoomed in and you have tunnel vision and
you're probably not at all times
considering enough different
perspectives all right
so make sure you figure out what that
lens is for you and adjust accordingly
when needed all right so if you are
typically working with fat loss clients
and now you have an athlete or client
that comes to you and wants to improve
their basketball performance you really
need to take the time to rethink all the
things you do the recommendations in the
prescription do you have regarding their
context not yours so to give you some
tangible examples of that I like to
think of it this way when you're trying
to look at the data or the science and
you're kind of come up with the right
answer well the data are what the data
are and there's really no arguing with
that unless you're a scientist and we
can argue over your study design your
methodology your staffs
if you're a general practitioner that's
not really your job but your job is the
next two pieces and that's
interpretation and context and those two
things are a matter of perspective
right now the authors of studies will
typically give you their interpretation
because they have a certain set of
perspectives but again please don't let
that influence yours so if you see us
see a study that shows hey carbohydrate
post exercise was better than carbs and
protein or wasn't better than carbs and
protein post exercise okay great those
are what the data arm but the
interpretation other words therefore
what's that mean it's up to you because
the only only you know your perspective
so you could then take that and say okay
great for a fat loss client maybe carbs
don't matter them but hey for a repeated
exercise individuals training twice a
day for their mountain bike race well
maybe that's a different answer etc all
right so please please please consider
how to interpret the data don't worry
about arguing with the validity of the
data too much you're not a scientist but
the interpretation and the context is up
to you and it is completely changed by
perspective so the analogy I'll give you
here is this this is of course a recent
incident where a Tesla was on autopilot
and actually drove into the side of a
building so even though we have some of
the best scientists in the world and
hundreds of millions of dollars and
engineers of the Yalu making these auto
driving cars and the science is
unbelievable and they're so incredibly
accurate 99% of the time you still can't
take your hands and eyes fully off the
wheel so I would say the same thing for
you even though you can follow some
scientists online and you can go to
conferences and clinics and there's some
really smart scientists out there don't
take your hands entirely off the wheel
right you still have to think right
don't let them drive your car on
autopilot for you you can let them get
you most the way there but keep your
eyes on the wheel still or your eyes on
the road your hands at least hovering
over that wheel because they may not be
able to always see exactly what's
happening in your world so that's why I
say nutrition science it's a bit like
autopilot mode on a Tesla pretty damn
good and there's some real sharp
scientists out there but always keep
your head in the game
so the lesson I hope you learned from
today's video is what I call amateur
scientists and armchair coaches so the
amateur scientists are the coaches and
practitioners who you look at some
science and think they know the answer
to everything right it's like well great
science showed you should always or the
post-exercise anabolic windows complete
garbage no that's not what the science
says I try not to over interpret science
like that if you're not scientist on the
flip side the armchair coaches so these
are scientists who do one study and
therefore think they know how to tell
all coaches what to what to do well
probably not because you're probably
only considering one training outcome
and not all the rest not logistics not
what it's like to actually work with the
human being and and all things all those
other considerations right and then
finally that nutrient timing is more
than just protein high perch
the vast majority of the conversation in
the nutrient timing world is sort of
fixated on that and I don't want and
that's important but I don't want you to
be disillusioned into thinking that's
the only consideration and therefore
quote protein chiming or nutrient timing
doesn't matter so to summarize what we
currently known the literature suggests
regarding post-exercise nutrients number
one it may not you may not need it
exactly post exercise or anything like
that but it doesn't hurt either all
right so there's no advantage to waiting
number two there if you're training
fasted maybe you want to consume those
essential amino acids or complete
proteins and carbohydrates and as soon
as you possibly can with a very little
fat however if you're training fed the
total amount of essential amino acids in
protein especially consumed throughout
the day or over a two day period it's
probably more important than timing
itself however the single goal is to
maximize recovery why not just maximize
the volume the carbs of protein all day
all right if you're just if you're in
the middle of season or really trying to
focus on recovery why skimp just get it
all there as much as possible try to top
off everything if the goal is to lose
weight though or fat loss more
specifically I would still concentrate
those those proteins amino essential
amino acids and carbohydrates around
your training and then cut your calories
on off days or on meals that are away
from your training that will help you
maximize your recovery maximize your
muscle growth or maintenance and repair
and you can still be in a hypo Clark
state if that's the goal hopefully
you've learned a little bit about this
exercise concept nutrition concept but
also you hopefully you've learned a
little bit more about the idea of being
in no immerses the learner so your
homework today from this video is to
google those terms and search that I
think we need a lot more people to
understand this concept and spend a lot
more time in one of these than the other
intent right so Google that around I'm
not going to walk you through it but
it's really really really important
thing for both science aside I think
scientists do an incredibly poor job of
this they get really stuck into one of
the categories here and then
practitioners tend to be a little bit
better but the science the scientists
community could really improve here
the Instagram models the influencers are
just epically terrible at this in fact
the whole job is to be completely on one
side of the equation and it convinced
you so hard to buy their stuff by acting
like they're they're really far down one
end of the spectrums right so I would
typically say this is another way for me
to advertise it better decision-making
on your part for your clients yourself
your athletes individuals is what I'll
call being wise and everybody we want to
be wise we don't want to be smart we
don't want to know things
so I don't have no information we want
to make better decisions right in order
to do that we have to have good quality
information good data we're gonna pay
attention to the science we got to go to
clinics and conferences and know what's
going on but we've got to combine that
with our understanding of context and
have some humility we don't know
everything we don't know every situation
and just because someone's making a
different decision than we think is good
we may not know everything that's going
on right and but the acknowledgement
that the reason we continue to study
things like this is we don't know
everything there are still pieces to
this information or pieces to this
scenario we don't know yet so as more
research comes out I may change my
position on some or all this stuff right
so there's always a little bit of
humility we have to have especially in
the fields of nutrition and and high
performance if you want to read more
about this topic I would strongly
encourage you to read ISSN International
Society sports nutrition a position
stand on a nutrient timing Chad Curt SiC
led this thing up and it's fantastic
they cover a lot of this stuff they go
deep into science if you want to know
that but they also give you really good
some ways and take homes with numbers
how many carbs how many protein with a
scenario different situations and all
that it's fantastic it's free it's open
access so good on you issn and and dr.
Kirk sick for for leading us up not
being said I appreciate the time and
we'll see you around next time be fill
please feel free to check out more of
these five 25 and 55 minute videos I got
all kinds of ones on nutrition strength
training programming general healthy
performance if you're digging these
things you know what to do
help me
all right see you later
[Music]